Register of the Jaroslav Stránský Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jaroslav Stránský papers,
1894-1970
82075
Stránský, Jaroslav, 1884-1973
8 manuscript boxes (3.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, radio broadcast transcripts, and correspondence, relating to politics and culture in Czechoslovakia, and to conditions in Czechoslovakia under communism.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (7 reels).
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1884 January 15 Born, Brno, Czechoslovakia
1907 Received his law degree from Charles University
1918-1925 Member of the Czechoslovak National Democratic Party
1918 October Member of the National Committee in Brno, which proclaimed Czechoslovakia independent
1918-1920 Represented the Czechoslovak National Democratic Party in the Revolutionary National Assembly
1918-1927 Owner and chief-editor of Lidové noviny
1920 Member of the Czechoslovak Parliament, Czechoslovak National Democratic Party
1921 March Resigned as member of the Czechoslovak Parliament
1921-1925 Leader of the Moravian Opposition Wing of the Czechoslovak National Democratic Party
1925 Resigned from the Czechoslovak National Democratic Party and founded the National Labor Party Became owner of the publishing house Fr. Borový in Prague
1929-1938 Member of the Czechoslovak Parliament, Czechoslovak National Socialist Party
1930 The National Labor Party merged with the Czechoslovak National Socialist Party
1938 September 30 Protested, along with a group of other parliament members, president Beneš's accepting the Munich Agreement
1938 December 16 Resigned as member of the Czechoslovak Parliament in protest against president Beneš's signing the Munich Agreement
1939 March Emigrated to Great Britain
1941 October 27 - 1942 November 12 State Minister for the Ministry of Justice of the Czechoslovak Government in exile
1942 November 12 - 1945 April 5 Minister of Justice of the Czechoslovak Government in exile
1945-1948 Member of the Czechoslovak Parliament, Czechoslovak National Socialist Party
1945 April 4-November 6 Minister of Justice in Fierlinger's Government in Prague
1945 November - 1946 Deputy Prime Minister of Czechoslovakia
1946 July 2 - 1948 February 25 Minister of Education in Gottwald's Government in Prague
1948 February 20 Resigned from his post as Minister of Education, and after the coup d'etat emigrated to Great Britain
1951-1970 Broadcast weekly commentaries on Radio Free Europe under the name of Jan Zedník
1973 August 13 Died, London, Great Britain
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jaroslav Stránský were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives from his son, Jan Stránský, in August 1982, and relate mainly to Stránský's anti-communist post-war émigré activities during the years he spent in his second exile. Shortly after the communist coup d'etat in February 1948 he emigrated to Great Britain, and in 1951 he started his regular broadcasts on Radio Free Europe.
The bulk of the collection consists of transcripts of these broadcasts on Radio Free Europe. From 1951 to 1970 Jaroslav Stránský delivered weekly commentaries to Czechoslovakia under the pen name Jan Zedník. His lively, often deeply philosophical speeches were objective, colorful, sober, and compassionate. He spoke about freedom and justice, spiritual and moral values, literature, theatre and art and their limited possibilities under the communist rule, and provided insightful analyses of the political and economic situation in Communist Czechoslovakia.
Of significant importance is Stránský's often very personal correspondence with prominent artists, writers, poets, composers, and politicians, such as Leoš Janácek, Arne Novák, Leopolda Dostálová, or Rudolf Bechyne, and reflects his life-long interest and involvement in the cultural and political life of the country.
The Lidové noviny file, a smaller but equally important part of the collection, relates to Stránský's activities as editor-in-chief of Lidové noviny, the daily newspaper founded by his father, Adolf Stránský. This series consists of letters written by artists and authors who contributed to the daily, and reflects their every day concerns about publishing issues.
Of special note are also Stránský's writings on the origins of the Czechoslovak exile, its crisis and tasks, as well as lectures on Czech and German relations.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Civilization.; Czechoslovakia--Politics and government.
Occupations
Statesmen--Czechoslovakia.
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1908-1966. (Box 1-2)
  Letters, notes, postcards, and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Lidové Noviny File, 1920-1946. (Box 2)
  Correspondence arranged under the names of the editor, František Šelepa, and of Jaroslav Stránský
- Speeches and Writings, 1950-1958. (Box 2)
  Articles, lectures, and speeches, arranged chronologically by title
- Radio Broadcasts File, 1951-1970. (Box 3-8)
  Transcripts of broadcasts on Radio Free Europe, arranged chronologically
- Adolf Stránský File, 1904-1931. (Box 8)
  Correspondence and obituaries of Adolf Stránský, father of Jaroslav Stránský, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Jan Stránský File, 1949-1964. (Box 8)
  Correspondence of Jan Stránský, son of Jaroslav Stránský, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 8)
  One print depicting Josef Beran, the Archbishop of Prague, and one postcard depicting Kácov nad Sázavou, signed by J. B. Čapek and E. Lukáč
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1908-1966 (Box 1)
  - Axman, Emil, 1926 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Bass, Eduard, 1923 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Bechyně, Rudolf, 1919-1937 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Beneš, Edvard, 1923-1944 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Beran, Josef, Archbishop of Prague, 1965-1966 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Bevin, Ernest, 1950 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Bezruč, Petr, 1913-1947 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Blažíček, Oldřich J., 1947 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Borský, Lev, 1919 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Brod, Max, 1929 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Burian, Karel, 1915 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Čapek, Josef, 1931 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Čapek, Karel, 1925-1930 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Čapek-Chod, Karel M., 1924 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Černý, Jan, 1924-1927 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Dostálová, Leopolda, 1946 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Dušek, Cyril, 1917 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Eisner, Pavel, 1935 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Engliš, Karel, 1933-1934 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Filla, Emil, 1926 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Fischer, Otokar, 1924-1928 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Florián, Josef, 1929 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Foerster, Josef Bohuslav, n.d. (Folder 1: 23)
  - Franke, Emil, 1929 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Gellner, František, n.d. (Folder 1: 25)
  - Hácha, Emil, 1934 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Herrmann, Ignát, 1923 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Houdek, Fedor, 1925 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Hubnerová, Marie, 1917 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Hýsek, Milan, 1909 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Janáček, Leoš, 1924-1927 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Jelínek, Hanuš, 1930 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Kameníček, František, n.d. (Folder 1: 33)
  - Kelsen, Professor, 1924 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Klofáč, Václav, 1930-1937 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Kordač, František, 1927 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Kvapil, Jaroslav, 1923-1938 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Laudová-Hořicová, 1913 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Lešehrady, Emanuel, 1947 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Mahen, Jiří, 1919 (Folder 1: 40)
  - Majerová, Marie, 1947 (Folder 1: 41)
  - Mařák, Otokar, 1928 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Markovič, Ivan, 1922 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Masaryk, Jan, 1924-1926 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Mičura, Dr., 1933 (Folder 1: 45)
  - Mixa, Vojtěch, 1925 (Folder 1: 46)
  - Nasková, Růžena, 1946-1947 (Folder 1: 47)
  - Nechleba, Vratislav, 1912-1913 (Folder 1: 48)
  - Novák, Arne, 1916-1938 (Folder 1: 49)
  - Novák, Vítězslav, 1947 (Folder 1: 50)
  - Olbracht, Ivan, 1933-1947 (Folder 1: 51)
  - Peroutka, Ferdinand, 1924 (Folder 1: 52)
  - Prečan, Leopold, 1946 (Folder 1: 53)
  - Pulda, J., 1910 (Folder 1: 54)
  - Rabas, Václav, 1946-1947 (Folder 1: 55)
  - Rádl, Emanuel, 1920-1928 (Folder 1: 56)
  - Rypáček, Jaroslav, 1910 (Folder 1: 57)
  - Schieszl, Josef? 1924-1925 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Sedláčková, Anna, 1946 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Sedlmayerová, Olga, 1936 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Sekanina, František, 1926 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Slovák, Alois, 1913 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Sova, Antonín, 1921-1922 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Svoboda, František Xaver, 1908-1923 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Šrámek, Fráňa, 1923-1947 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Štech, Václav, 1934 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Švabinský, Max, 1931-1946 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Talich, Václav, 1946 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Trýb, Antonín, 1928-1946 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Tusar, Vlastimil, 1922 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Veris, Jaroslav, 1931 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Vodák, J., 1922 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Vojan, Eduard, 1913-1915 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Vrchlická, Eva, 1932 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Weiner, Richard, 1919-1934 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Weyr, Professor, 1917-1923 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Zrzavý, Jan, 1928-1931 (Folder 2: 20)
- LIDOVÉ NOVINY FILE, 1920-1946
  - Šelepa, František
    - Averčenko, Arkadij, 1922 (Folder 2: 21)
    - Čapek, Karel, 1921-1935 (Folder 2: 22)
    - Dostál-Bystřina, Ferdinand, 1924 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Stránský, Jaroslav
    - Boettinger, Hugo, 1921-1924 (Folder 2: 24)
    - Chesterton, Gilbert Keith, 1926 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Durych, Jaroslav, 1921-1946 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Herben, Jan, 1925 (Folder 2: 27)
    - Herriot, Edouard, n.d. (Folder 2: 28)
    - Jahoda, Jaroslav, 1933 (Folder 2: 29)
    - Jirásek, Alois, 1920 (Folder 2: 30)
    - Kisch, Egon Erwín, 1924 (Folder 2: 31)
    - Křička, Petr, 1922 (Folder 2: 32)
    - Lolek, S., 1924 (Folder 2: 33)
    - Neumann, Stanislav, 1928 (Folder 2: 34)
    - Rais, Karel, 1923 (Folder 2: 35)
    - Těsnohlídek, Rudolf, 1925-1927 (Folder 2: 36)
    - Tilschová, Anna Marie, 1922-1925 (Folder 2: 37)
    - Toman, Karel, 1926 (Folder 2: 38)
    - Wolker, Jiří, 1922 (Folder 2: 39)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1950-1958
  - Speech on Czech-German relationship, n.d. (Folder 2: 40)
    Typescript (in English)
  - "The Czechs and the Germans," lecture, Frankfurt, Germany, 1950? (Folder 2: 41)
    Typescript (in German)
  - "Problém zásadní," lecture, London, Great Britain, 1950? (Folder 2: 42)
    Typescript (in Czech)
  - "Příčiny exilu a účel exilu," lecture, Frankfurt, Germany, 1950 February 10. (Folder 2: 43)
  - "Ke krisi v československé emigraci," lecture, Ústav Dra. E. Beneše pro politické a sociální studium, London, 1950 February 26. (Folder 2: 44)
  - "O naši nezávislost," Skutečnost, Paris, 1950 December 12. (Folder 2: 45)
    Printed copy (in Czech)
  - "Plamínková a Horáková," speech, Národní dům, London, 1952 June 20. (Folder 2: 46)
  - "O sudetoněmecké otázce," lecture, Ústav Dra. E. Beneše pro politické a sociální studium, London, 1953 January 16. (Folder 2: 47)
    Typescript (in English and Czech)
  - "Politický doslov a úvod," lecture, Ústav Dra. E. Beneše pro politické a sociální studium, London, 1954 April 11. (Folder 2: 48)
  - "Československo dnes a zitra," lecture, London, 1958 January 1. (Folder 2: 49)
- RADIO BROADCASTS FILE, 1951-1970. (Box 3)
  Consists of typewritten and handwritten transcripts of broadcasts on Radio Free Europe
  - 1951 (Folder 3: 1-2)
  - 1952 (Folder 3: 3-4)
  - 1953 (Folder 3: 5-6)
  - 1954 (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
  - 1955 (Folder 4: 3)
  - 1956 (Folder 4: 4-5)
  - 1957 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - 1958 (Folder 5: 3-4)
  - 1959 (Folder 5: 5-6)
  - 1960 (Folder 5: 7-8)
  - 1961 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
  - 1962 (Folder 6: 3-4)
  - 1963 (Folder 6: 5-6)
  - 1964 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
  - 1965 (Folder 7: 3-4)
  - 1966 (Folder 7: 5-6)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
  - 1968 (Folder 8: 3-4)
  - 1969 (Folder 8: 5)
  - 1970 (Folder 8: 6)
- ADOLF STRÁNSKÝ FILE, 1904-1931.
  - Correspondence
    - Kramář, Karel, 1904-1925. (Folder 8: 7)
      Includes a handwritten note by both T. G. Masaryk and Karel Kramář, exchanging views on the fate of Subcarpathian Ruthenia
    - Masaryková, Alice, 1923 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Sís, František, 1917 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Obituaries, 1931 (Folder 8: 10)
- JAN STRÁNSKÝ FILE, 1949-1964.
  Correspondence
  - Churchill, Clementine, 1950 (Folder 8: 11)
  - Davies, Ernest, 1950 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Desai, Morarji Ranchodji, 1963-1964 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Hankey, Robin, 1949 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Horák, Bohuslav, 1950 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Macmillan, Harold, 1950 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Sandys, Duncan, 1950 (Folder 8: 17)
  - Shuckburg, Evelyn, 1950 (Folder 8: 18)
  - Younger, Kenneth, 1950 (Folder 8: 19)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d.
  - One print depicting Josef Beran, the Archbishop of Prague (Folder 8: 20)
  - One postcard depicting Kácov nad Sázavou, signed by J. B. Čapek and E. Lukáč (Folder 8: 21)